Guide to the Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories 2018.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories
January 24, 2018 - January 22, 2019
Brooklyn Historical Society
Ali, Zaheer
Kitto, Svetlana
2018.006
8.32 Gigabytes in 149 files; Running time of available interviews: 103 hours, 19 minutes, and 27 seconds. All recordings and transcripts were born-digital.
This collection includes oral histories conducted and arranged by Brooklyn Historical Society in 2018. The interviews reflect varying approaches to religious observance among Muslim Brooklynites in relation to a wide range of communities and traditions within Islam, including Sunni, Shi'i, Sufi, Nation of Islam, W. D. Mohammed community, Five Percent, Dar ul Islam, and Ansaarullah. Collectively, there is particular focus on cultural and religious customs, practices, and gender roles within these communities; education and the arts; immigration from South Asia and the Middle East; the Nation of Islam; Islamophobia in the wake of the 1993 and 2001 terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center as well as after the 2016 presidential election; political activism and engagement; and community relations with law enforcement and government officials.
Arrangement
This collection was organized chronologically by interview date.
Biographical / Historical
In 1907, a community of Lipka Tatar immigrants from Eastern Europe founded the American Mohammedan Society in Brooklyn. Over the next few decades, the borough's first mosques were established, including both the American Mohammedan Society's Brooklyn Moslem Mosque in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn and the Islamic Mission of America on State Street (also known as Dawood Mosque) in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. By the second half of the twentieth century, policy changes and political volatility on the national and global stages greatly expanded the presence of Muslims in Brooklyn through large waves of both spiritual and physical migrations.
The Nation of Islam's resurgence among African Americans throughout the 1950s and 1960s was particularly strong in New York, whose Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan was home to one of the Nation of Islam's largest temples. By 1963, the Nation of Islam's New York Minister Malcolm X had opened mosques elsewhere in the city, including Mosque No. 7C (later known as Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah) in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. The community underwent significant reforms following the transfer of leadership from Elijah Muhammad upon his death in 1975 to his son Warith Deen Mohammed, including a shift toward Sunni Islam tenets. These changes ultimately led to local and national rifts within the Nation of Islam, and were a catalyst for the establishment of Masjid At-Taqwa in 1981, also located in Bedford-Stuyvesant.
Brooklyn's Muslim immigrant communities also experienced significant growth during that time. The American Immigration and Nationality Act of 1965 abolished quotas that favored primarily Christian countries in Europe, broadening the geographic and religious diversity among immigrants to the United States. Successive waves of immigration included greater proportions of emigrants from primarily Muslim countries in Africa and Asia, many of whom settled in Brooklyn. In the following decades, many communities blossomed, including (but not limited to) Muslim Pakistani communities in the Brighton Beach and Flatbush neighborhoods of Brooklyn, the Muslim Bangladeshi communities in the Kensington and East New York neighborhoods of Brooklyn, and interfaith Arab communities in the Midwood and Bay Ridge neighborhoods of Brooklyn.
Islamophobia became more pronounced after the 1993 and 2001 terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center in Manhattan. Harassment, detentions, and deportations rose, and in the years following the September 11, 2001 terrorist attack, the New York Police Department pursued a policy of religiously-motivated surveillance of Muslim communities throughout the city. After the surveillance was revealed, the Raza v. City of New York lawsuit was filed in June 2013 on behalf of some of the Brooklyn-based individuals and institutions whose religious or social missions had been harmed by policy. The courts ultimately found in the plaintiffs' favors, requiring the city to pay damages and make significant changes to their policies surrounding surveillance of religious groups going forward.
Attacks on Muslim communities also escalated when 2016 Republican presidential candidate Donald Trump proposed a ban on all Muslim people entering the country. After he took office, his administration crafted Executive Order 13769, and despite a series of court challenges, including the Supreme Court ruling in Trump v. Hawaii allowed implementation of most of the ban. During this period, hate crimes against Muslim Americans also increased across the United States, including in Brooklyn.
The social and institutional hostility directed at many Muslim Americans throughout that period, especially during the early part of the twenty-first century, sowed significant anxiety and suspicion among many in Muslim communities. Consequent fears for their safety and security led some Muslim Americans to withdraw from public life. For others, it contributed to a surge in activism, political engagement, charitable work, advocacy, and involvement in cultural institutions. Many Muslim Brooklynites in particular were leading voices in these efforts, including Linda Sarsour's co-chairing the nationwide Women's March on Washington in 2017 for equality and Debbie Almontaser's leadership in organizing the Yemeni Bodega Strike at Brooklyn Borough Hall in 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection can be accessed onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online at the Oral History Portal.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These oral histories were conducted by staff or consultants at the Brooklyn Historical Society in 2018.
Scope and Contents
The Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories include interviews with narrators with roots in a number of Muslim communities in Brooklyn. These narrators reflect the diversity that is characteristic both of Brooklyn's population in general and of Muslim Brooklynites in particular: they include immigrants and their immediate descendents from different regions across all five continents as well as African Americans; represent a wide variety of approaches to their faith within several different traditions of Islam, including Sunni, Shi'i, Sufi, Nation of Islam, W. D. Mohammed community, Five Percent, Dar ul Islam, and Ansaarullah; and span in age from 24 to 74.
These narrators discuss their overall experiences in neighborhoods across Brooklyn as well as their involvement in nearly a dozen of the city's religious institutions from the mid-1960s until 2018. Collectively, many of them also emphasize their personal relationships with their Muslim faith, including the degree and approach of their observance over time; the teachings and philosophies that speak most strongly to them; the intersection between religion and cultural traditions; cultural norms and education specific to their community's tradition; and building relationships with people of other faiths. There is also significant emphasis on their encounters with Islamophobia, particularly following the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001 and the United States' 2016 presidential election, as well as the social and political activism it inspired from several narrators in the collection as well as from many Muslim Americans across the country.
Arab Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islam and art -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamic education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim converts -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religion and culture; Religious pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; South Asian Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam; Kensington (New York, N.Y.); Interviews (sound recordings); Oral histories (document genres); Transcripts; Brooklyn College; American Mohammedan Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Five Percent Nation; Islamic Mission of America (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid At-Taqwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Ahmad Jaber, January 24, 2018; 2018.006.01
  Biographical / Historical
  Ahmad Jaber was born in 1947 in the city of Jenin in Palestine during a period of changing political boundaries. He earned a medical degree from Mosul University in Iraq in 1972. When political unrest prevented him from returning to Jenin, he practiced medicine in Jordan and then immigrated to the United States. Following successful completion of his post-graduate studies and residency, he married his wife and began a private OB/GYN practice in Brooklyn. He also maintained a strong presence in several religious and cultural institutions in Brooklyn, including co-founding the Arab American Association of New York and taking on a leadership role in the Islamic Mission of America (also known as the State Street Mosque).
  Scope and Contents
  In this interview, Ahmad Jaber discusses his early life, including his mother's struggle to support the family following his father's death, his immigration to the United States following Israel's occupation of the West Bank, and his medical education. He also talks extensively about the role of his faith and ethnicity in his professional life, especially regarding co-founding the Arab American Association of New York, his advocacy for a dedicated Muslim prayer room at the Lutheran Medical Center, and his efforts to support women's education and health in culturally sensitive ways. In addition, he speaks in depth about his ongoing involvement in New York's Muslim and interfaith Arab American communities, especially the Islamic Mission of America (also known as the State Street Mosque) and the New York Chapter of the National Arab American Medical Association. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This interview can be accessed onsite at the Center for Brooklyn History's Othmer Library and online at the Oral History Portal.
  Arabs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Prayers and devotions; Islamic education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jenin; Muslim physicians -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Palestinian Arabs -- West Bank; Religion in the workplace -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women's health services -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Al-Noor School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Arab American Association of New York; Islamic Mission of America (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Jaber, Ahmad; Masjid Dawood (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); National Arab American Medical Association; NYU Lutheran Medical Center; State Street Mosque (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Debbie Almontaser, February 10, 2018; 2018.006.02
  Debbie Almontaser was born in Yemen. Her family immigrated to the United States when she was a toddler and settled in Buffalo, New York. She married her husband and moved to the Cobble Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1980. Her involvement with her child's primary school inspired her to pursue a career in education, eventually becoming the founding principal of the Khalil Gibran International Academy in Brooklyn. She also became a prolific activist, including coordinating New York City's first Arab-American Heritage Week in 2005; founding the Bridging Cultures Group, Inc. in 2015; supporting Democratic nominee Hillary Clinton's 2016 presidential campaign; and organizing the Yemeni Bodega Strike at Brooklyn Borough Hall in 2017. Throughout her work as both an educator and an activist, she put significant focus on multicultural and interfaith partnerships, also founding and participating in a number of groups and initiatives aimed at increasing empathy across racial, ethnic, and religious lines. She earned a bachelor of the arts in English and world religions from St. Francis College in Brooklyn; a master of the sciences in multicultural education and reading from Adelphi University in Manhattan; and a doctor of education in urban education and leadership from Fordham University in the Bronx.
  In this interview, Debbie Almontaser discusses her Yemeni American family, including her childhood in Buffalo, New York; her marriage to her husband; and raising their children in the Cobble Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn. She also talks about her career in education, including her early work as a paraprofessional and teacher for the New York City Board of Education; her collaborative efforts with the Board of Education, the New Visions for Public Schools non-profit organization, and the Arab American Family Support Center to create the Khalil Gibran International Academy, an Arabic dual language secondary school in Brooklyn; and the circumstances surrounding her resignation and subsequent community protests in her defense. She speaks at length about her relationship with her faith; experiences at the State Street Mosque in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn; and work to build interfaith relationships within her community, especially between Muslim Americans and Jewish Americans. In addition, she remembers being a teacher in Brooklyn during the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001, and elaborates extensively about subsequent increases in Islamophobia and racial profiling. Debbie Almontaser was also interviewed for this collection on May 14, 2018. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Arab Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hijab (Islamic clothing) -- New York (State); Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamic education of children -- New York (State) -- New York (State); Islamophobia -- New York (State); Jewish-Arab relations; Muslim educators -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public Schools -- Employees; Racial profiling in law enforcement -- New York (State) -- New York; Religious education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Buffalo (N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- New York; Women political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Yemeni Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Arab American Family Support Center, Inc. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Islamic Mission of America (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Khalil Gibran International Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New Visions for Public Schools (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Board of Education; State Street Mosque (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United States. Department of Education; Almontaser, Debbie
- Oral History Interview with Hassan Ben Jaafar, February 12, 2018; 2018.006.03
  Hassan Ben Jaafar was born in 1962 in Fès, Morocco. He studied music under his father, following in his footsteps to become a Maâlem (master musician). After coming to New York in 2000, he collaborated with a wide variety of musicians, performing both individually and with his band, Innov Gnawa.
  Hassan Ben Jaafar discusses his early life in Morocco, especially regarding his culture and his musical education through his father's school. He also speaks about coming to New York City, especially to the Red Hook neighborhood of Brooklyn. He expands on his musical influences; performances in a variety of venues across New York City, and work with his band, Innov Gnawa. He also talks about his memories of the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001; surviving a house fire; being robbed while working at a store; and involvement in Masjid Farooq in the Boerum Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn. This interview includes extensive conversation in Moroccan Darija. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Boerum Hill (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Fès (Morocco); Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); Arabic language -- Dialects -- Morocco; Gnawa (African people); Moroccans; Music -- Moroccan influences; Performing arts; Robbery -- New York (State) -- Kings County; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001
- Oral History Interview with Ferial Masoud, February 13, 2018; 2018.006.04
  Ferial Masoud was born in 1950 in the city of Jerusalem during a period of changing political boundaries. She immigrated to the United States after marrying her husband in 1972. After settling in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn, they owned a series of small businesses, the most notable of which is the Balady Halal Market.
  In this interview, Ferial Masoud shares her memories of growing up in Jerusalem, including the detrimental impact the Six-Day War had on her safety and the broader culture of Jerusalem. She also speaks about her marriage to her husband, her feelings of isolation following her immigration to the United States, and her efforts to maintain her American-born children's link to their culture. In addition, she talks extensively about her husband's small businesses in Brooklyn, especially the Balady Halal Market, and their family's work to make the businesses successful. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Americanization; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Grocery trade -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrant business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Jerusalem; Muslim families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Palestinian Arabs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Small businesses -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Masoud, Ferial; Balady Halal Market (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Asad Dandia, February 16, 2018; 2018.006.05
  Asad Dandia was born in 1992 in Brooklyn, and was raised by his Pakistani family in the Brighton Beach neighorhood of Brooklyn. While attending Brooklyn College as an undergraduate, he co-founded the nonprofit charity Muslims Giving Back. Over the course of the next several years, he became involved with a number of other activist and religious organizations, including Make the Road New York and the Center for Spiritual Life at New York University (NYU). In 2013, Dandia joined the Raza v. City of New York class action lawsuit that successfully sued the New York City Police Department for its prejudicial surveillance of Muslim communities, including Muslims Giving Back.
  In this interview, Asad Dandia discusses his experiences growing up in a close-knit Pakistani American community in Brighton Beach, including his involvement in a local mosque. He also talks about his involvement in the volunteer-based Muslims Giving Back charity, the negative impact the New York City Police Department's religiously-motivated surveillance had on Muslim communities throughout the city, and his participation in the resulting class action lawsuit brought by the American Civil Liberties Union and Creating Law Enforcement Accountability and Responsibility at the CUNY School of Law. In addition, he speaks about his college experiences and involvement in other activist organizations, including a strong focus on both his religious convictions as a Muslim and affinity for interfaith groups and ideas. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Class actions (Civil procedure) -- New York (State) -- New York; Communities -- Religious aspects -- Muslims; Faith-based human services -- New York (State) -- New York; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- New York; Pakistani Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- New York; Racial profiling in law enforcement -- New York (State) -- New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brighton Beach (New York, N.Y.); September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; American Civil Liberties Union; Creating Law Enforcement Accountability and Responsibility. City University of New York; Global Spiritual Life (New York University); Islamic Center (New York University); Masjid Omar (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Muslims Giving Back (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York Civil Liberties Union; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Rahman, Shamiur
- Oral History Interview with Siraj Wahhaj, February 19, 2018; 2018.006.06
  Siraj Wahhaj was born in 1950 in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. He joined the Nation of Islam in 1969 and became the imam of Masjid Muhammad 7C in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1976. Two years later, he studied with the Muslim World League in Chicago, Illinois and at Umm Al-Qura University in Mecca, Saudi Arabia. He founded Masjid At-Taqwa in 1981, and purchased a building in Bedford-Stuyvesant to house the mosque the following year. As the imam of Masjid At-Taqwa, he coordinated successful efforts to reduce crime in the area, especially through anti-drug patrols in January of 1988, and also emphasized significant community outreach. He was the first Muslim to give an opening prayer for the United States House of Representatives in 1991, and in 2004, he founded the Muslim Alliance in North America (MANA) to advocate for Muslim Americans' needs and civil rights. He also served on the city's Majils As-Shura Islamic Leadership Council of New York, campaigned for New York City public schools to formally recognize Muslim Eid holidays, and represented Masjid At-Taqwa in the Raza v. City of New York lawsuit against the New York City Police Department for religiously-motivated surveillance.
  In this interview, Siraj Wahhaj discusses the impact of Martin Luther King Jr.'s assassination on his feelings about nonviolent protests; his exploration of the Nation of Islam as a young adult; his attendance and activities at the Nation of Islam's Muhammad Mosque No. 7C in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn; and his experiences with Louis Farrakhan, Warith Deen Mohammed, and other leaders of the movement. He elaborates about becoming the imam of Muhammad Mosque No. 7C after it was renamed Masjid Muhammad 7C; studying Islam in Illinois and Saudi Arabia; the circumstances of his leaving Masjid Muhammad 7C; and his founding Masjid At-Taqwa in Bedford-Stuyvesant. He also speaks extensively about the anti-drug patrols he coordinated at Masjid At-Taqwa, his experiences with local law and federal enforcement, and the importance of integrating Islam into American culture as a mainstream religion. In addition, he touches on his family, childhood, and early education. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.